let's look at the solution to our dram
access scheduling quiz so we have 32
arrays each is 16 megabits and takes a
12 bit row address and a 12 bit column
address
12 bits
is 3 hex digits so the row address will
be the upper three hex digits and the
column address will be the lower
hex digits each of these
corresponds to a 32-bit memory location
so what happens is each of these arrays
sees the same address but it provides a
different bit for that address so each
address will have the same sequence of
row and column addresses it's just that
they will implement different bits of
that address so what we have here is the
first one of course needs to be at page
open
so we have 10 nanoseconds to open this
first page
we will then read
in two nanoseconds
then we will close the page
in another five nanoseconds because the
next one is on a different page
the row address is different
so we spent 17 nanoseconds here we will
spend another 17 here
we will then spend another 17 here
because it's again a different row
17 here
and here and here and here overall we
have seven accesses each to a different
page
so each of them requires
17 nanoseconds
for a total of
119 nanoseconds now let's try to
reorganize these what we want to do when
we reorganize these
is once we open a page access everything
on that page before we move on which
means
we will open this row
and then we will access everything in
that row which means this
and this two
now what happens is we spend ten
nanoseconds opening that row
three times two nanoseconds
reading these three things
and then we need to close the row in
another 5 nanoseconds
then what happens is we open the next
row and we read everything from that row
which includes this two
so we end up opening one row reading two
things from it and then closing it and
now we spend
17 nanoseconds for each one of these
in total
we spent 74 nanoseconds
doing these accesses so as you can see
when caches have a number of pending
misses and we need to send these misses
to memory
it pays to rearrange the order of the
addresses we are accessing to benefit
from the organization of the dram